[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
Here's a whole village living in one room.
यहां पूरा एक गांव एक ही कमरे में रह रहा
This is our room.  At least six
है। यह है हमारा कमरा। इसमें कम से कम छह
families live in it.  There has been war going on in our Manipur for two years.
परिवार रहते हैं। हमारे मणिपुर में दो साल
Here people are just eating dal and rice.
से वॉर चल रही है। यहां लोग बस दाल चावल
Children are studying by setting up tents.
हैं। बच्चे टेंट लगाकर पढ़ाई कर रहे हैं।
So this is for 100 people.  Yes.  Please don't go
सो दिस इज फॉर 100 पीपल। यस। प्लीज डोंट
late.  I feel very uncomfortable.  It's
गो देर। आई फील वैरी अनकंफर्टेबल। इट्स
okay kids.  Is your village in front?  O our
ओके किड्स। आपका गांव सामने है? ओ हमारा
village is just here in front.
गांव इधर ही सामने।
And now you can't go to the village you see there in front
और अब आप वहां सामने जो गांव दिख रहा है
?  Can't go.  This is
वहां नहीं जा सकते? नहीं जा सकते। यह है
Manipur where there are 170 relief camps.  My team
मणिपुर जहां 170 रिलीफ कैंप्स हैं। इन्हीं
reached there to show the truth about the people trapped in these.
में ठुसे लोगों की सच्चाई दिखाने पहुंची
We have just passed six check points here.
मेरी टीम। यहां हमने अभी छह चेक पॉइंट्स
Where we are staying.  This shows that
हैं। जहां पे हम रुके हैं। यह बताता है कि
even after 2 years the conditions here are
अभी भी 2 साल बाद यहां कंडीशंस नॉर्मल तो
not normal.  2 years ago it was a market place.  A
नहीं है। 2 साल पहले ये एक मार्केट प्लेस
market used to be held here.  But now people are
था। यहां पे बाजार लगता था। पर अभी लोग
living here using mosquito nets and bedsheets.  This is where my husband, my
पर रह रहे हैं। यह मेरा पति सोएगा, मेरा
baby and I will sleep.  My father-in-law and
बच्चा और मैं सोएगा। वहां पर मेरा ससु
my elder brother will sleep there.  Sister will also sleep there
मेरा माजी सोएगा। वहां पर भी दीदी सोएगा
who sells clothes after everyone has gone to sleep.
जो बेचना पदार लगाता है सब सोने के बाद।
What do you want for your child?
अपने बच्चे के लिए आप क्या चाहते हो?
We want a good future for the children
बच्चों के लिए अच्छी भविष्य चाहता है हम
because we feel that he is my
लोग क्योंकि हम लोगों की मन करता है मेरा
child, if he asks for something to eat then
बच्चा है ना वो कुछ खाने के लिए दे मांगा
we could not give it to his mother, that is why
तो हम लोग मां को दे नहीं पाया ना इसलिए
seeing this condition we have gone
बहुत ये हालत देख के हम लोगों का दिमाग
crazy, how will we make him a
खराब हो गया है कैसे बनाएगा हम लोग उसको
big man
आदमी बड़ा सा आदमी
[Music] Not only were the
[संगीत]
houses that the people of Manipur built with years of hard work snatched away, but their
घर बनाए वो तो छीने ही साथ ही में उनका
work was also snatched away which is their means of earning a living
काम भी छीना जो जो एक रोटी खाने का साधन
and then they were not just separated from the roof of their houses.  He was
होता है और फिर उनको सिर्फ अपने घर की छत
even distanced from his own family members.  Who all are there
से अलग नहीं किया। अपने ही घर वालों से भी
in your house?
दूर कर दिया गया। आपके घर में कौन-कौन है?
Our wife is in Susapur right now.  Why does your wife have to
हमारा बीवी अभी सुसापुर में है। आपकी बीवी
live separately?  But it
को अलग क्यों रहना पड़ रहा है? लेकिन अलग
was a different caste.  Do you talk to me?  Yes.  Sometimes it's been a
जाती था। आपकी बात होती है? हां। कभी दो
year or two longer.  The point is not to not meet.  I have
एक साल ज्यादा हो गया। बात नहीं मिलना
n't even done it.  There is a slight restlessness in the heart.  If
नहीं है। फ़ भी नहीं करा है। दिल में थोड़ा
those people do the right work and not politics
दौरत होता है। राजनीति नहीं वो लोग सही
then no one will be harmed.
काम करेगा तो नुकसान कोई किसी को नहीं
A. Don't do it.  Don't fight.
होगा। ए मत करो। लड़ाई मत करो। चुपचाप
Keep quiet.  One should live in peace.  By talking like this
रहो। शांति से रहना चाहिए। ऐसा बात करने
everything will remain peaceful.  We will keep
से सब शांति से रहेगा। हम लोग दोनों को
beating both of them.  What will be getting?  You will not
मारते मारते रहेगा। क्या मिलेगा? कुछ नहीं
get anything.  Your blood is red.  My blood
मिलेगा। तुम्हारा खून लाल है। मेरा खून भी
is also red.  There is only one God.  Man has been
लाल है। भगवान तो एक ही है। आदमी ने नाम
making different names.   There is
अलग-अलग बना रहा है।
a temple just outside this camp where
इस कैंप के ठीक बाहर एक मंदिर है जहां
food is cooked for 1500 people.
1500 लोगों का खाना बनता
But in the name of food,
है। पर खाने के नाम पर पिछले दो सालों से
only dal and rice has been available here for the last two years.
यहां बस दाल चावल ही पहुंच पाया है।
What is being made here right now?  Just now the
अभी क्या बन रहा है यहां पे? यहां अभी
morning dal and rice has been cooked here and now we
सुबह का दाल चावल बना है और अभी हम लोग
cook food here for 1500 people.   There
यहां खाना बनाते हैं 1500 आदमी के लिए।
is no opportunity to work here.
यहां काम करने का मौका भी नहीं मिलता है।
That's why we are cooking food for the relief camp here.
इसलिए हम लोग यहां रिलीफ कैंप का खाना बना
Where are you from?  From Churachandpur.
रहे हैं। आप कहां से हैं? चुराचंदपुर से।
What did you do there?  We were laborers there.  He
आप वहां क्या करते थे? वहां पर हम लेबर
builds a house there.  Is your job to
थे। घर बनाता है वहां पे। आपका काम घर
build a house?  Yes.  And what happened to your house
बनाने का है? हां। और आपके घर के साथ क्या
?  Everything was burnt.  Everything is over there.
हुआ? सब जला दिया। सब खत्म हो गया वहां पर
Now there is no one left there.  Away from their own family members,
अब वहां पर कोई बचा नहीं। अपने घर वालों
these people cook food for other people's families.
से दूर ये लोग दूसरों के घर वालों के लिए
Only dal and rice is prepared
खाना बनाते हैं। बनता सिर्फ दाल चावल है
but still people stand in line and wait with utensils in their hands.  There is
लेकिन फिर भी इसके लिए लाइन लगा के बर्तन
an under construction building behind me
मेरे पीछे एक अंडर कंस्ट्रक्शन बिल्डिंग
and this relief camp is also here.
है और यहां पे भी यह रिलीफ कैंप है। यहां
People are living here also.  Sir, since when have you been living
पर भी लोग रह रहे हैं। सर कब से आप रह रहे
here?
हैं यहां पे?
We are in our village since 23rd May, the Manipuri
हम 23 मई महीने से हमारा गांव तो मणिपुरी
people burnt everything on fire, that is why we ran away and came here.
लोग आग जला दिया सब इसलिए हम भाग के आ जाए
How does it feel to live here?
कैसा लगता है यहां रहने पे मजा
My wife is sick, her stomach is sick. There is not
है हमारा पत्नी बीमार है उसका पेट बीमार
even a fan here. No, there is no fan
है यहां पंखा भी नहीं है नहीं पंखा नहीं
from there. When the house burnt, only a few things could be saved and
है कोई वहां से जब जला घर तो कुछ बचा के
brought, everything was burnt.  No,
ला पाए सब सब जल गया। नहीं सब जल
Manipur has a population of only 30 lakh people.
मात्र 30 लाख लोगों की आबादी है मणिपुर
But still how come it is so difficult to maintain peace here
में। पर फिर भी यहां पीस मेंटेन करना इतना
?  11,000 houses burnt, more than 250
मुश्किल कैसे? 11,000 घर जले, 250 से
lives lost.  But still our national
ज्यादा जाने गई। पर फिर भी हमारे नेशनल
media never told the story of Manipur.  At
मीडिया ने ना मणिपुर की कहानी कभी नहीं
that.
सुनाई। एट दैट। जब कॉन्फ्लिक्ट चल रहा था,
I was living in Imphal when the conflict was going on.  And your
तब मैं इंफाल में रहती थी। एंड योर
parents?  When the conflict started, we
पेरेंट्स? जब कॉन्फ्लिक्ट शुरू हुआ, हम
ran away separately.  Because of this our name got
अलग-अलग भागे। इस वजह से हमारा नाम यहां
registered here and theirs there.  That's why
और उनका वहां रजिस्टर हो गया। इसीलिए अब
we can't live together anymore.  How does it feel living here
हम साथ नहीं रह सकते। यहां रहकर कैसा लगता
?   It is a
है?
bit uncomfortable but I think
थोड़ा अनकंफर्टेबल है पर मुझे लगता है
God has thought of something for us.  He does
भगवान ने हमारे लिए कुछ तो सोचा है। वो
not do anything wrong because we are his
कुछ गलत नहीं करते क्योंकि हम उनके ही
children.  Now I don't miss home
बच्चे हैं। अब मैं घर मिस नहीं करती
because the way we were treated there was
क्योंकि जैसे हमें वहां ट्रीट किया वो
very bad.  But when I
बहुत ही बुरा था। पर जब मैं अपने बचपन के
think about my childhood I miss it a lot.
बारे में सोचती हूं तब बहुत याद आती है।
And this is our kitchen.
एंड दिस इज आवर किचन।
We cook for here.
वी कुक फॉर हियर।
Here water also has to be filled from tankers
यहां पानी भी इस तरह टैंकर से भरना पड़ता
and sometimes when tankers do not come, people have to
है और कई बार टैंकर भी नहीं आते तो लोगों
fill water from the pond.  The
को पोंड से पानी भरना पड़ता
water is so dirty, there is a
है। जो पानी इतना गंदा होता है
fight between two communities here.
यहां लड़ाई दो कम्युनिटीज के बीच है।
Mehti and Kuki and this fight started in 2023 itself
मेहती और कुकी और यह लड़ाई 2023 में ही
when the Mehti community
शुरू हो गई थी जब मेहती कम्युनिटी ने
demanded to become a Scheduled Tribe.  People have
शेड्यूल ट्राइब बनने की डिमांड रखी। पीपल
doubt that weather I am may and weather I am
इज डाउट दैट वेदर आई एम मे और वेदर आई एम
from the cooking
फ्रॉम द कुकिंग
side.  I've been struggling from nightmarish
साइड। आई हैव बीन स्ट्रगलिंग फ्रॉम नाइट
sleep walks then like a sudden bang of
मेयरर्स स्लीप वॉक देन लाइक अ सडन बैंग ऑफ
sound really scares me.  I will see people
साउंड रियली स्केर्स मी। आई विल सी पीपल
dying in my dreams.  I will see people
डाइंग इन माय ड्रीम। आई विल सी पीपल
killing each other and I will be stealing there
किलिंग ईच अदर एंड आई विल बी स्टेलिंग देर
and watching them.  Shooting each other.
एंड वाचिंग देम। शूटिंग ईच अदर।
We cannot even imagine what
हम ना यह सोच भी नहीं सकते कि कैसा होगा
that scene would be like that still scares Kajal and many others like her.
वो मंजर जो काजल और उसके जैसे कई लोगों को
One night my child was
आज भी डरा देता है। एक रात मेरे बच्चे की
very unwell.  Suddenly
तबीयत काफी खराब थी। एकदम से हमारे पूरे
tear gas started entering our entire house.  My sick
घर में टियर गैस घुसने लगी। मेरा बीमार
child wasn’t even moving anymore.  I
बच्चा अब हिल भी नहीं रहा था। मैंने उसे
tried to wake him up but he wouldn't get up.
उठाने की कोशिश की लेकिन वो उठा ही नहीं।
Deadly gas and fire had spread rapidly throughout the house.
पूरे घर में डेडली गैस और आग तेजी से फैल
My mother was also in my house
चुकी थी। मेरे घर में मेरी मां जी भी थी
but she could not walk.  I then ran away from home to save my life along with my 5-
लेकिन वो चल नहीं सकती थी। मैं तब मेरे 5
month old child and mother.
महीने के बच्चे और मांजी को लेकर जान
Here people are forced to live in schools, colleges,
यहां लोग मजबूर हैं स्कूल्स, कॉलेजेस,
markets and even under construction
बाजार और यहां तक कि अंडर कंस्ट्रक्शन
buildings.
बिल्डिंग तक में रहने के लिए।
S bag
स बाग
manipur
मणिपुर
manipur S bag
मणिपुर स बाग
manipur ko
मणिपुर को
mpur langi mani
मपुर लंगी मनी
nik
निक
manipur m
मणिपुर म
this guy is junior to me in high
दिस गाय इज जूनियर टू मी इन हाई हाई
school.  He was shot down on the night
स्कूल। ही वास् शॉट डाउन ऑन द ऑन द नाईट
of May 3rd, I think he was just a few
ऑफ़ थर्ड मई, आई थिंक ही वास् जस्ट अ फ्यू
meters away from his house when he was
मीटर्स अवे फ्रॉम हिज़ हाउस व्हेन ही वास
shot dead.  Today many such Walls of
शॉट डेड। आज मणिपुर में कई ऐसी वॉल्स ऑफ़
Remembrance can be seen in Manipur.  These are the Kuki, Methi,
रिमेंब्रेरेंस दिखेंगी। ये वो कुकी, मेथी,
Manipuri, you Indians who
मणिपुरी, आप भारतीय हैं जिन्होंने इस
lost their lives in this conflict.  Whose
कॉन्फ्लिक्ट में अपनी जान गवाई। जिनकी
faces remained only in these pictures.  These two
शक्लें बस इन तस्वीरों में रह गई। दीज़ टू
young women were earning their livelihood by
यंग वुमेन वर अर्निंग देयर लाइवलीहुड बाय
working in a car wash.  The two were raped at
वर्किंग इन अ कार वाश। दी टू वर रेप्ड एट
the same time and were killed.
द सेम टाइम वर किल्ड।
When a man is filled with hatred he becomes
आदमी जब नफरत से भर जाता है ना तो एक भूखे
as scary as a hungry animal.  Then he
जानवर जैसा डरावना हो जाता है। तब उसे
sees the crowd, but the faces of the crowd
भीड़ तो दिखती है पर भीड़ का चेहरा धुंधला
become blurred.  And today this helpless crowd is on both sides.
हो जाता है। और आज ये बेबस भीड़ दोनों तरफ
[MUSIC]
[संगीत]
What do you think is the possible solution to
व्हाट डू यू थिंक इज़ द पॉसिबल सलूशन टू
bring everything back to normal?  It's
ब्रिंग एवरीथिंग टू नॉर्मल सी? इट्स
normal it may be a little
नॉर्मल
difficult since two years
सी मे बी लिटिल डिफिकल्ट सिंस टू इयर्स
already and then they have been you know most
ऑलरेडी एंड देन दे हैव बीन यू नो मोस्ट
and then they are raped and then naked raped, after all this
एंड देन दे रेप एंड देन नेकेड रेप आफ्टर
I don't think there should be peace
ऑल दिस आई डोंट थिंक्स देयर शुड बी पीस
again.
अगेन।
Perhaps if this much violence had happened in any other Indian
शायद इतना वायलेंस अगर किसी भी और इंडियन
state, it would have been talked about everywhere.
स्टेट में होता तो उसकी बात हर जगह होती।
But the people of Manipur have been left at the mercy of time.
पर मणिपुर के लोगों को सिर्फ वक्त के